[Music]
a number of artificial sweeteners have
been fda approved in north america
including aspartame and sucralose sold
to splenda but there are also natural
high-intensity sweeteners found in
plants the global market for
non-nutritive sweeteners in general
these non-caloric sweeteners is in the
billions including all the artificial
ones and
two natural ones extracted from plants
stevia and monk fruit
i've done a video about stevia what
about monk fruit
fruits of lua hong guo
monk fruit in chinese have evidently
been used for hundreds of years is a
natural sweetener in folk medicine
the non-caloric sweet taste comes from
mogrisa it's a group of cucurbitain type
chertapine glycosides make up about one
percent of the fruit and are like
hundreds of times sweeter than sugar the
mixed moga sides have been estimated to
be about 300 times as sweet as
table sugar such that an 80 extract was
nearly 250 times sweeter than sugar
if you read reviews in chinese natural
medicine journals you'll see
pronouncements like this monk fruit has
been shown to have anti-coughing effects
anti-asthma anti-oxidation liver
production blood sugar lowering
immunoregulation and anti-cancer
but what they don't tell you up front
is that they're talking about reducing
ammonia induced mouse coughs
a natural food sweetener with
anti-pancreatic cancer properties monk
fruit may be used for daily consumption
as an additive in foods and drinks to
prevent or treat pancreatic cancer
yeah maybe in your pet mouse
and the anti-proliferative activity
among fruit and colorectal cancer and
throat cancer was on colorectal and
throat cancer cells in a petri dish
now they did show mogasides killing off
colorectal cancer cells and throat
cancer cells and look our digestive
tract could be directly exposed to these
compounds if we ate them
but what's missing
right they didn't test it against
cells i mean you could pee in a petri
dish and kill off cancer cells the whole
point is to find something that kills
off cancer but leaves normal cells alone
something that they weren't able to show
here
are there any human studies on monk
fruit
no
until
now
owing to the rapidly growing popularity
of natural plant-based sweeteners they
thought it would be of interest to
determine whether natural sweeteners
would be a healthier alternative to
sugar or artificial sweeteners so they
randomized people to drink an aspartame
sweetened beverage
versus monk fruit sweetened versus
stevia versus table sugar
and then they measured blood sugars over
24 hours
and there was no significant difference
found
between any of them
but wait a second
the sugar group was given 16 spoonfuls
of sugar the amount of added sugar in a
20-ounce bottle of coke
so the other three groups consumed 16
less spoonfuls of sugar
and still had the same average blood
sugars
but table sugar caused a big blood sugar
spike
here it is i'll show you
drink that bottle of sugar water with
its 20 sugar cubes worth of sugar
and your blood sugars jump 40 points
over the next hour
whereas you give an aspartame sweetened
beverage or monk fruit or stevia and
nothing happens which is what you'd
expect right these are non-caloric
sweeteners no calories
it's just like you're drinking water
right
so how could your daily blood sugar
values average out the same i mean the
only way that could happen
is if the non-calorie sweeteners maybe
made your blood sugar spikes worse
somehow later in the day
look what happens
when you give people splenda mixed with
sugar water you get a greater blood
sugar spike a greater insulin spike
chugging the sugar with sucralose than
without even though splenda alone causes
no spike of its own
so does aspartame do the same thing
at the one hour mark they fed people a
regular lunch
and so the blood sugars went back up and
down as they normally would after a meal
not spiking as high as drinking straight
sugar water just a gentle up and down
okay
but that was in the group that drank the
sugar an hour before in the group that
drank the aspartame
even though their blood sugars didn't
rise at the time an hour later at lunch
they shot up higher
as if the person just drank a bottle of
soda
okay but what about the natural
sweetener stevia and monk fruit
same thing same exaggerated blood sugar
spike to a regular meal taken an hour
later
so you can see how it all equals out in
terms of average blood sugars even
though in these three non-caloric
sweetener groups
they took in 16 spoonfuls less sugar
at least in part because they ate more
after drinking a diet coke you're more
likely to eat more at your next meal
than drinking a regular coke in fact so
much more that the energy saved from
replacing sugar with non-caloric
sweeteners was fully compensated for at
a subsequent meal hence no difference in
total daily calorie intake was found
the sugar sweetened beverage led to
large spikes in both blood sugar and
insulin whereas these responses were
higher for three other beverages
following the lunch later
so when it came to calorie intake or
blood sugars or insulin spikes they were
all just
as
bad
[Music]
foreign